graduated from college, went to work for Ford Motor Company for several years, then got a job at the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints and moved back to Salt Lake City. During that employment, I had the opportunity to be loaned out to the state's largest homeless shelter to assist them in developing and improving their financial and management capabilities. While there, I became aware of a new approach to dealing with homeless individuals and drug addicts. It was called the harm reduction model, and it consisted of passing out clean needles and condoms. And I thought, "Now that is one stupid idea." (Laughter) "That's just going to encourage them to continue that behavior. Just tell them to stop." Several years later, I read some of the early 10-year plans to end chronic homelessness promoted by the federal government. As I read through those plans, and I thought, "Pfft! This is unrealistic. You can't end homelessness. There's too many personal choices and factors beyond our control." My perspective changed, however, when I attended a conference in 2003, where I learned the reason behind the 10-year plan. First was this small population of the homeless group that was 15 percent and were very expensive. That made sense for a conservative state like Utah. The second insight was learning about this Housing First, or low-barrier housing. There had been an agency in New York City that had been inviting mentally ill homeless individuals to move directly from the street into housing. And they were also allowed to continue to use drugs and to drink, just like we can in our homes. They were, in addition, offered services -- not required to use them -- by on-site case managers to assist them to adjust to their new living arrangements and to stabilize their lives. They were using the harm reduction model. And despite my initial low expectations about hearing about this model, they were having an astonishing success rate: 85 percent were still housed after 12 months. The third insight was the importance of developing a trusting relationship. Because of the abuse these individuals have had throughout most of their lives, they hardly trust anybody, and the clean needles and condoms and low-barrier housing was a means to begin to develop a relationship of trust. Vital. So as I flew home from this conference, sitting in the plane looking out the window, I realized that my understanding and perspective about homelessness was shifting. And as I stared out that window, this very strong feeling and thought came to me that if there's any state in the union that could end chronic homelessness, it was the state of Utah, because there's an underlying feeling and desire and willingness to collaborate to serve our neighbors, including those who are homeless. A new vision was becoming clear to me how this could be done. Now, those of us that attended the conference said, "Yeah, these models will work in Utah." But when we got back home, there were many who said, "Nah, those aren't going to work. They won't succeed here." But there was, however, an affordable housing organization who was willing to build our first 100 units. But they had concerns about having 100 chronically homeless people in one location. To address that concern, we decided to create a pilot to test that idea while we built the first 100 units. We would use existing units scattered throughout Salt Lake City. Then we debated: Should we select fairly high-functioning homeless persons or the most challenging ones we could find? And this is where my background on the ranch came into play. Back then, my mother cooked our meals and heated the water for our weekly bath on a wood-burning and coal-burning stove. And after chopping wood for that stove all those years, I'd learned to chop the big end of the log first, when I had the most energy. We decided to use the "big end of the log first" approach and selected 17 of the most challenging, difficult, chronically homeless people we could find, because we knew we would learn the most from them. Twenty-two months later, all 17 were still housed, including Keta, who today, 11 years later, is sleeping in her own bed and is sober. At the end of this pilot, one of the young case managers said, "We used to debate up at our university classes which theory of case management was the most effective. Now our theory of case management is: anything necessary to keep them housed." We became believers, and built hundreds of units over those next 10 years, leading to the reduction of our statewide chronic homeless population of 91 percent. Now, who are homeless people? Many people just want them to go away, to disappear, not disrupt our lives. Through this 10-year, 11-year process, I gained many insights of why people become homeless. One of those insights came to me a few years ago when I was visiting with our medical outreach team. These are our frontline workers that go out and visit the street homeless and the prostitutes to check on their medical health. One of the team members mentioned that eight of the prostitutes had given birth to 31 children that had become wards of the state. They also shared that some of the pimps were their husbands, and worse yet, their parents. These prostitutes, in their late teens, 20s, early 30s, were expected to earn enough money a day to support a hundred-dollar-a-day heroin addiction, their living expenses and their pimp. And with unprotected sex, they were paid more, and predictably, this would lead to a pregnancy. Children born under these circumstances many times end up becoming homeless. And it's not helpful to look at those born under those circumstances, or a parent that makes their child a drug addict at age seven, or a generation of babies born through drug addiction, and not feel some despair. For me, I believe every person is of value, no matter who you are. And it's not helpful to look at somebody with this start in life and blame them for where they are. (Applause) No one grows up saying, "My goal in life is to become homeless." And that's the beauty of the harm reduction and Housing First model. It recognizes the complexities of the different factors that can shape a human life. These models meet people where they are, not where we are or where we think they should be. The pilot we did with our 17 taught us many lessons. When people have been living on the street for many years, moving back into housing requires lots of things to learn. And Donald taught us some of these transition lessons. His case manager asked him why he had not turned up the heat in his cold apartment. Donald said, "How do you do that?" He was shown how to use a thermostat. The case manager also observed that he was heating the beans in the can on the stove, like he had done over the campfires for many years. He was shown how to use pots and pans. We also learned that he had a sister that he had not seen in 25 years, who thought he was dead. She was happy to learn otherwise, and they were soon reconnected. Hundreds of people like Keta and Donald are now housed and reconnecting with their families. Also, many of our communities are incurring fewer emergency services costs. I have learned over and over again that when you listen to somebody's story with an open heart, walk in their shoes with them, you can't help but love and care for them and want to serve them. This is why I'm committed to continuing to bring hope and support to our homeless citizens, who I consider to be my brothers and sisters. Thank you. (Applause)
me gradué de la universidad, trabajé para Ford Motor Company durante varios años, luego trabajé en la Iglesia de Jesucristo de los Santos de los Últimos Días y regresé a Salt Lake City. En ese empleo tuve la oportunidad de que me asignaran al refugio más grande para personas sin hogar del estado para ayudarlos a desarrollar y mejorar sus capacidades financieras y de gestión. Mientras estaba allí, vi un nuevo enfoque para tratar con personas sin hogar y drogadictos. Se llamaba el modelo de reducción de daños, y consistía en repartir agujas limpias y condones. Y pensé: "Sí que es una idea estúpida". (Risas) "Eso los va a alentar a continuar con ese comportamiento. Solo díganles que paren". Varios años después, leí algunos de los primeros planes a 10 años para terminar con la carencia de hogar promovido por el gobierno federal. Mientras leía esos planes, pensé, "¡Pfft! Esto no es realista. No puedes acabar con la falta de vivienda. Hay demasiadas decisiones personales y factores fuera de nuestro control". Mi perspectiva cambió, sin embargo, cuando asistí a una conferencia en 2003, donde aprendí la razón detrás del plan a 10 años. Primero fue esta pequeña población del grupo de personas sin hogar que era un 15 % y era muy costosa. Eso tenía sentido para un estado conservador como Utah. La segunda idea fue conocer de este programa Housing First, o vivienda muy asequible. Había una agencia en la ciudad de Nueva York que había estado invitando a personas sin hogar con enfermedades mentales a pasar directamente de la calle a la vivienda. Y también se les permitió continuar usando drogas y bebiendo, como nosotros en nuestros hogares. Además, se les ofrecieron servicios, --no era obligatorio usarlos--, de trabajadores sociales para ayudarlos a adaptarse a su nueva forma de vivir y a estabilizar sus vidas. Estaban usando el modelo de reducción de daños. Y a pesar de mis bajas expectativas iniciales al escuchar sobre este modelo, estaban teniendo una tasa de éxito sorprendente: el 85 % todavía estaban alojados después de 12 meses. La tercera idea era la importancia de desarrollar una relación de confianza. Debido al abuso que estas personas han tenido durante la mayor parte de sus vidas, casi no confían en nadie, y las agujas limpias y los condones y la vivienda asequible era un medio para comenzar a desarrollar una relación de confianza. Vital. Mientras volvía a casa de esta conferencia, sentado en el avión mirando por la ventanilla, me di cuenta de que mi comprensión y perspectiva sobre la falta de vivienda estaba cambiando. Y mientras miraba por la ventanilla, este sentimiento y pensamiento muy fuertes vinieron a mí que si hay algún estado en la unión que podría terminar con la carencia crónica de hogar, era el estado de Utah, porque hay un sentimiento subyacente y el deseo y la voluntad de colaborar para servir a nuestros vecinos, incluidos aquellos sin hogar. Una nueva visión me fue aclarando sobre cómo se podría hacer esto. Quienes asistieron a la conferencia dijeron: "Sí, estos modelos funcionarán en Utah". Pero cuando volvimos a casa, hubo muchos que dijeron: "Nah, eso no va a funcionar. No tendrán éxito aquí". Pero hubo, sin embargo, una organización de vivienda asequible que estuvo dispuesta a construir nuestras primeras 100 unidades. Pero les preocupaba tener a 100 personas crónicamente sin hogar en un solo lugar. Para afrontar esa preocupación, decidimos crear un piloto para probar esa idea mientras construíamos las primeras 100 unidades. Utilizaríamos las unidades existentes diseminadas por Salt Lake City. Luego debatimos: ¿Deberíamos seleccionar personas sin hogar que funcionaran bastante bien o los más desafiantes que pudiéramos encontrar? Y aquí es donde entraron en juego mis antecedentes en el rancho. Por entonces, mi madre cocinaba nuestras comidas y calentaba el agua para nuestro baño semanal en una estufa de leña y carbón. Y después de cortar leña para esa estufa por muchos años, había aprendido a cortar primero el extremo más grande del tronco, cuando yo tenía la mayor energía. Decidimos usar el enfoque "primero el extremo grande", y seleccionamos a los 17 más desafiantes que pudimos encontrar, personas difíciles, crónicamente sin hogar, porque sabíamos que aprenderíamos más de ellos. Veintidós meses después, los 17 todavía estaban alojados, incluyendo Keta, quien hoy, 11 años después, está durmiendo en su propia cama y está sobria. Al final de este piloto, uno de los trabajadores sociales dijo: "Solíamos debatir en nuestras clases universitarias qué teoría de trabajo social era la más efectiva. Ahora nuestra teoría de trabajo social es: cualquier cosa necesaria para mantenerlos alojados". Nos convertimos en creyentes, y construimos cientos de unidades en los siguientes 10 años, llevando a la reducción de nuestra población crónicamente sin hogar a nivel estatal al 91 %. Ahora, ¿quiénes son las personas sin hogar? Muchas personas solo quieren que se vayan, desaparezcan, que no alteren sus vidas A través de este proceso de 10, 11 años, obtuve muchas ideas de por qué las personas se vuelven sin hogar. Una de esas ideas me vino hace unos años cuando estaba visitando con nuestro equipo médico. Son nuestros trabajadores de primera línea que visitan en la calle a los sin hogar y a las prostitutas para verificar su salud médica. Uno del equipo comentó que 8 de las prostitutas habían dado a luz a 31 niños que se habían quedado bajo tutela del estado. También compartieron que algunos de los proxenetas eran sus maridos, y peor aún, sus padres. Estas prostitutas, en su adolescencia tardía, 20 años, principios de los 30, se esperaba que ganaran suficiente dinero al día para mantener una adicción a la heroína de cien dólares al día, sus gastos de vida y su chulo. Y con el sexo sin protección, les pagaban más, y predeciblemente, esto llevaba a embarazos. Los niños nacidos en estas circunstancias muchas veces terminan sin hogar. Y no es útil mirar a los nacidos bajo esas circunstancias, o un padre que hace que su hijo sea un drogadicto a los siete años, o una generación de bebés nacidos por adicción a las drogas, y no sentir algo de desesperación. Yo creo que todas las personas tienen valor, no importa quién eres. Y no es útil mirar a alguien con este comienzo en la vida y culparlo por donde está. (Aplausos) Nadie crece diciendo: "Mi objetivo en la vida es llegar a ser un sin hogar". Y esa es la belleza de la reducción de daños y el modelo Housing First. Reconoce las complejidades de los diferentes factores que pueden formar una vida humana. Estos modelos encuentran a las personas donde están, no donde estamos nosotros o donde creemos que deberían estar. El piloto que hicimos con nuestros 17 nos enseñó muchas lecciones. Cuando la gente ha estado viviendo en la calle por muchos años, al volver a la vivienda requiere aprender muchas cosas. Y Donald nos enseñó algunas de estas lecciones de transición. Su trabajador social le preguntó por qué no había subido el calor en su frío apartamento. Donald dijo: "¿Cómo haces eso?". Le mostró cómo usar un termostato. El trabajador social también observó que estaba calentando los fríjoles en la lata en la estufa, como lo había hecho en las fogatas por muchos años. Le mostró cómo usar ollas y sartenes. También aprendimos que tenía una hermana que no había visto en 25 años, que pensó que estaba muerto. Ella se puso feliz de saber lo contrario, y pronto se reconectaron. Cientos de personas como Keta y Donald están alojadas y reconectadas con sus familias. Además, muchas de nuestras comunidades están incurriendo en menores costos de servicios de emergencia. He aprendido una y otra vez que cuando escuchas la historia de alguien con el corazón abierto, caminas en sus zapatos con ellos, no puedes evitar amarlos y cuidarlos y querer servirlos. Es por eso que estoy comprometido en continuar brindando esperanza y apoyo a nuestros ciudadanos sin hogar, a quienes considero mis hermanos y hermanas. Gracias. (Aplausos)